<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Mock Funeral</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2021-02-15T17:16:09+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>mh</name>
   <email>mockfuneralmh@gmail.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Stephan Mathieu interview</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/15/stephanmathieuinterview"/>
   <updated>2021-02-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/15/stephanmathieuinterview</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h5 id=&quot;words-and-interview-by-rm&quot;&gt;Words and interview by RM.&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I read about Marc’s idea for a blog about “old macs“, Stephan Mathieu was on my mind right away. His oeuvre has a few references such as “The sad mac“, “FrequencyLib“, “Kapotte Muziek by Stephan Mathieu“ that somehow fit the topic and knowing how some of them came to live, it also fits the connotation of obsolete technology that might fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/stephanmathieu1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stephan Mathieu&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6 id=&quot;stephan-mathieu-2001-credit-bryony-mcintyre&quot;&gt;Stephan Mathieu 2001. Credit: Bryony McIntyre&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephan Mathieu’s debut “Wurmlochvariationen” was recently re-released on Weeding,  a Irish label. Originally released on CD on Ritornell in 2000, it is a collection of hypnotic tracks made out of aliasing and bitcrushed samples, sequenced carefully with subtle fades and layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephan’s music evolved over 20 years from the gritty textures to more ethereal blanket like sound objects. His love for entropic systems is also another highlight in my opinion, it is beautifully documented on the “Trace“ compilation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=766946626/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=de270f/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://schwebung.bandcamp.com/album/trace-recordings-of-entropic-systems-1998-2018-2cd&quot;&gt;Trace. Recordings of Entropic Systems 1998-2018 | 2CD by Stephan Mathieu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reached out to Stephan to get some more details. Here they are…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which software did you enjoy most when you were using a Powerbook/OS9?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was always a ProTools user, pre-OSX ProTools Free was my favorite since it was the most reliable version. I also used Max/MSP, actually my first version came with floppy disc authorisation.
Even though I studied this for a while, I never really wrote my own tools, simply because I learned rather quickly that I simply lack ideas of what I want to build! What I made for myself was a tool that helped me with the live entropy which is of course time consuming. Play file &amp;gt; record through mic &amp;gt; play new recording &amp;gt; record through mic &amp;gt; etc.
Other than that I used a handful of patches build buy friends, whereas what I did with them sounded completely different to what they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the difference of this older software compared to more recent software?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Then there is spectral editing which is now a breeze with Spectralayers and just as powerful as Photoshop. I want to switch from ProTools to Wavelab since it’s so much more handy when it comes to the routine tasks in mastering like tagging, exporting, assembling the master if various formats but I’m slow with the learning while I can handle PT in my sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/stephanmathieu2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stephan Mathieu 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I see some lovely tools like Argeiphontes Lyre and Soundhack listed on Frequency Lib…&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I made my first computer based production early in ‘95, still as a drummer with my friend Lupo in a brand new Protools driven studio where we had recorded, processed, mixed and mastered an EP entirely in the box.
Since this was the studio’s maiden voyage we were able to work there pretty much around the clock for over a week. Back then I was not interested in computers, but at the end of day 1 I thought that I don’t want to go to a studio for this, I want this myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It took about 2 years until I buy my first Mac, the just released PowerMac 7300 running Protools 3 through an Audiomedia III interface and I found working in Protools surprisingly easy based on what I had learned 2 years earlier. My initial plan was to use the computer for live processing of my drum kit and also to record the upcoming album with my former band in our living room. First thing I did though was recording our piano. I’m not a pianist, so this was rather me playing chords by eye and ear, the tune that became Wurmloch.
The same night I copied those 11 minutes through my room, recording 26 generations I’m
Sitting In A Room style as material for a commissioned outdoor installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Next was recording my drums, but I ended up using only a snippet with one single hit on my floor tom to explore the plugins that came with PT, time stretch, Lo-Fi, Sci-Fi, Recti-Fi and the Orange Vocoder. The snippet became 11.55.330, and I was seriously hooked with DSP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=842174793/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=de270f/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://schwebung.bandcamp.com/album/1155330&quot;&gt;11.55.330 by Stephan Mathieu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the same time I discovered Argeiphontes Lyre and Soundhack and started processing the Wurmloch piano piece for what became the Variations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=4071736094/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=de270f/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://schwebung.bandcamp.com/album/wurmloch-variationen&quot;&gt;Wurmloch Variationen by Stephan Mathieu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;With AL I love the esotherics and poetry involved and the one of a kind sound of the filters, with Soundhack it was the convolution algorithms that interested me since they seemed familiar to the analog entropic processes I was fascinated with since a while, but as a powerful digital beast that melts audio much differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ArgeiphontesLyre1.jpg .jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Argeiphontes Lyre&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Also Soundhack’s Header Change is something I used heavily to alter pitch and duration of material. This also lead to some heavy aliasing noise which I loved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/soundhack08.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Soundhack 0.8&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I had quite the steep learning curve with digital audio and in 1998 got in charge of an traditional electronic music studio in France, just across the border from where I lived. Apart from setting up their collection of analog synths and gear I had the chance to build a grown up Protools system based on their brand new 888 24 24-Bit interface where I would teach and digitize their archive of reels, DAT tapes and cassettes and was also able to work on my own stuff. The studio was associated with the GRM in Paris, so I had their GRM Tools available to play with and we also got Max/MSP and later their Pluggo suite once they became available. By that time I also got my first laptop, a Pismo along with a 24-Bit mobile interface, the Digigram VXPocket so I could work in my little home studio and easily bring the material to France to finish the pieces. Full Swing Edits, a series of reworks of other peoples music was done that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At some point I got really tired of using plugins as effects and also of arranging and fine-tuning pieces. Even my more complex pieces involved no more than 3 stereo tracks but I wanted to be less in control of the audio. By that time Full Swing Edits and Wurmloch Variationen had been released and I noticed that I would hear every decision I made during production and this sounded to forced to me. I started developing a system based on AL, Soundhack and MSP where the final output was a realtime stream that I would record over long durations and then select the best parts which I would EQ with a Calrec RQQ 2200 until they sounded right to me, sometimes over months. Die Entdeckung des Wetters on Lucky Kitchen was one result of this, later on Radioland which I had in the making between 2002-04.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 100%; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=736013629/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=de270f/tracklist=false/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://schwebung.bandcamp.com/album/radioland-2&quot;&gt;Radioland by Stephan Mathieu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the end I’ve always used Protools for recording and editing, with AL, Soundhack and MSP as my processing tools while only the source material had varied until I stopped making music some years ago. I never felt the need for more processing power and used my computers until they died. I enjoy working with a very limited pallette. There was a time when I thought Kyma would be good to have, but after spending a while with a friend’s Capybara several years ago I again noticed that I simply lack the vision of what I want to do with the tools. What I’d love to see is a 2021 version of Tom Erbe’s convolution
algorithms, this should be really inspiring on a modern computer and would probably get me back to working on music. I just love convolution of audio and entropy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://macintoshgarden.org/apps/pro-tools-free-501-oms&quot;&gt;Pro Tools Free at MacintoshGarden.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Xynthi (2006)</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/11/xynthi"/>
   <updated>2020-12-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/11/xynthi</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/xynthibanner1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;xynthi header small&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Written by mh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xynthi is a Supercollider patch made by Bhob Rainey, released as a stand-alone executable in 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patch is made to (visually at least) emulate the EMS Synthi series of synthesizers from the early 70s, but it’s not aimed to be a sonically faithful recreation of it. Which would probably be quite the fruitless task. Though the pin matrix works much the same as on the Synthi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This patch is the entire reason I got an old 2002 Powerbook to begin with. I wrote about it in &lt;a href=&quot;https://mockfuneral.github.io/2020/12/08/introduction&quot;&gt;the introduction post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m struggling to find the fitting words. I don’t want to over-exaggerate, but I really do love this patch. I’ve gotten so much useful material out of it and it’s pretty fun to explore. It can create grating digital textures, bleeps, bloops and lovingly soft and hellishly harsh drones. In the audio section further down I’ve added some of my work using the patch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the included README:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Xynthi is a universal build, so you’ll need 10.3.9 or higher to run it.  you’ll know it’s working if you can open it, load an included preset, and hear something crazy coming through your speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it didn’t work under macOS 10.13.6 (High Sierra), but I’ve heard of another slightly different version that somehow did run on that OS. I can’t say for sure. I will update if I find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote an email to Rainey to ask him for a link I could share for this blog (see the links section) and to ask for a Paypal address, should people want to donate to him. He sent me back a nice email explaining why it never got beyond its current state, which I am putting here with permission from Rainey himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe that the only reason it doesn’t work in the current macOS is the switch to only accept 64-bit apps. It may be possible to do a 64-bit build and have it work. What I’d really like to do is just host the code on GitHub, so that anyone who has a working version of SuperCollider could use the app. That’s a medium-sized project, since SC switched to .scd files instead of .rtf, many of the GUI elements have changed, and the fact that you can’t define classes on-the-fly in SC means that some custom classes would have to be converted to class-like structures like Events. A mildly nauseating set of tasks that I just haven’t had the time and stomach to get to.
I do have PayPal at this address (lloydlyson@gmail.com). I think that, in the entire time since Xynthi was released, which is at least 12 years, one person has sent me a payment of around $10. Never make your target audience a bunch of experimental noise dudes if you want to make a buck :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lighthearted end. I trust there must be some experimental noise dudes reading this. I sent him some bucks after the email, since I’ve used Xynthi a whole lot more than some of my paid applications and pieces of software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forever evaluating?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/k2r8zuihih45uba/Xynthi.zip?dl=0&quot;&gt;Download Xynthi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bhobrainey.com/&quot;&gt;Bhob Rainey’s website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;audio&quot;&gt;Audio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“ALL BENT OUT OF SHAPE” (2019).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 400px; height: 241px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=904229178/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=333333/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://marchasselbalch.bandcamp.com/album/all-bent-out-of-shape&quot;&gt;ALL BENT OUT OF SHAPE by Marc Hasselbalch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Strong Whip (Versatile)” (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 400px; height: 208px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=506369187/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=333333/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://marchasselbalch.bandcamp.com/album/strong-whip-versatile&quot;&gt;Strong Whip (Versatile) by Marc Hasselbalch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Brushed Steel Minesweeper” (2020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 400px; height: 241px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=488036132/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=333333/artwork=small/transparent=true/&quot; seamless=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://marchasselbalch.bandcamp.com/album/brushed-steel-minesweeper&quot;&gt;Brushed Steel Minesweeper by Marc Hasselbalch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“April 3” (2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 400px; height: 120px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1081154272/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=333333/tracklist=false/artwork=small/track=3112541910/transparent=true/&quot; seamless=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://marchasselbalch.bandcamp.com/album/lockdown-march-13-april-14&quot;&gt;Lockdown (March 13–April 14) by Marc Hasselbalch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“March 14” (2020)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0; width: 400px; height: 208px;&quot; src=&quot;https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1081154272/size=large/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=333333/artwork=small/track=849651184/transparent=true/&quot; seamless=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://marchasselbalch.bandcamp.com/album/lockdown-march-13-april-14&quot;&gt;Lockdown (March 13–April 14) by Marc Hasselbalch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;screenshots&quot;&gt;Screenshots&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blank patch
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/xynthi_osx_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Xynthi1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noisy, scratchy patch
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/xynthi_osx_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Xynthi2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xynthi running on OSX 10.3.9 on a titanium Powerbook G4 from 2002.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/xynthipowerbook1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Xynthi running on OSX 10.3.9&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>SoundMaker and SoundMagicFX plugins (1997)</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/09/soundmakersoundmagicfx"/>
   <updated>2020-12-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/09/soundmakersoundmagicfx</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/soundmagicfxicons.png&quot; alt=&quot;SoundMagicFX icons&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Written by mh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SoundMaker by Alberto Ricci is sound editor for Mac (68k and PPC), released in 1997. It is the commercial upgrade to his earlier free software, SoundEffects, from a few years prior.
I have tried to get in contact with Ricci since I started using the software, but no luck so far. I found an email address on his old 2003 website, but, unsurprisingly, it didn’t go through. It seems he might work at Apple these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SoundMagicFX by Michael Norris is a suite of plugins for SoundMaker. The plugins are still available for download at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.michaelnorris.info/soundmagic/download.html&quot;&gt;Michael Norris’ website&lt;/a&gt;, but the shareware plugins folder requires a password and, when imported into SoundMaker, requires a registration code to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon realizing this, I contacted Michael Norris and asked if I could obtain a license. He got back to me, but unfortunately he didn’t remember the password after all these years. Further research into the plugins led me to an interview with Markus Popp/Oval, who apparently was using SoundMaker and the Norris plugins in the late 90s. So I contacted him and asked if he had them somewhere on an old machine. Not more than a day later he got back to me with the passwords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have received permission from Michael Norris himself to share the password for the shareware folder and registration code here. But please do understand that these are not supported anymore and have long since been replaced by his realtime plugins, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.michaelnorris.info/software/soundmagic-spectral&quot;&gt;SoundMagic Spectral.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;shareware-effects-bundle-archive-password&quot;&gt;“Shareware Effects” bundle archive password:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;chrysalis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;registration-code&quot;&gt;Registration Code:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;75279888&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you end up using this, please consider donating to Norris himself at michael.norris@vuw.ac.nz&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The non-realtime rendering of SoundMaker reminds me of working in Composer’s Desktop Project/CDP, though CDP seems to process even slower, even on a modern laptop. But I really am liking this very different way of working. Load up a file, load up a process, adjust, wait for 10-60 seconds, result. Listen, adjust, process, result. Because of the limited memory of my Powerbook, I can’t really go nuts with the processes, as it will quickly run out of memory and tell me so right away. So I find myself working with quite short audiofiles, which I then process and save different versions of for later use. So I end up having this little sound bank after each SoundMaker session that I can then arrange, re-sample, whatever, on my modern laptop (which, as of this post, is from 2012). I really don’t mind the DAW puzzle micro-arrangement workflow, since it really forces me to work with and perceive time on a wholly different scale. I wonder if this will push me to compose very short pieces. Micro works. Time to finally pick up a copy of Microsound I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://macintoshgarden.org/apps/soundmaker-103&quot;&gt;SoundMaker 1.0.3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://riccisoft.com/soundeffects/&quot;&gt;SoundEffects 0.9.2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.michaelnorris.info/soundmagic/download.html&quot;&gt;SoundMagicFX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://riccisoft.com/&quot;&gt;Alberto Ricci’s site (Not updated since 2003)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.michaelnorris.info/&quot;&gt;Michael Norris’ site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.michaelnorris.info/soundmagic/effects.html&quot;&gt;SoundMagicFX documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tips-and-findings&quot;&gt;Tips and findings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When putting in the shareware folder password, I had to try two different compression tools on my modern laptop, as the first one (which might have been the macOS standard one) didn’t accept the password, but another one did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have tried Ricci’s SoundEffects, but it is quite lacking compared to SoundMaker. It doesn’t even feature an ‘undo’ function. I tried to import the SoundMagicFX plugins into SoundEffects, but they don’t show up. In case you wanted to try it out. So as of now I haven’t found any reason to use SoundEffects over SoundMaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first imported the SoundMagicFX plugins into SoundMaker, it took me a while to realize that most - if not all - of the GUIs for the proccesse, both standard and Norris ones, didn’t output. It just used the default GUI settings every single time. Trashing the preference folder and re-registrering did the trick and now everything works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;audio&quot;&gt;Audio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few examples of what I had lying about. If you’d like to add your own more interesting examples, get in touch.
Input for all of these examples is acoustic guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/944144827&amp;amp;color=%236c6c6a&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral&quot; title=&quot;Mock Funeral Audio&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;Mock Funeral Audio&lt;/a&gt; · &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral/soundmaker-soundmagicfx-4&quot; title=&quot;SoundMaker &amp;amp; SoundMagicFX:  Strum 1a&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;SoundMaker &amp;amp; SoundMagicFX:  Strum 1a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/944144821&amp;amp;color=%236c6c6a&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral&quot; title=&quot;Mock Funeral Audio&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;Mock Funeral Audio&lt;/a&gt; · &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral/soundmaker-soundmagicfx-3&quot; title=&quot;SoundMaker &amp;amp; SoundMagicFX: Strum 1b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;SoundMaker &amp;amp; SoundMagicFX: Strum 1b&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/944144815&amp;amp;color=%236c6c6a&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral&quot; title=&quot;Mock Funeral Audio&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;Mock Funeral Audio&lt;/a&gt; · &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral/soundmaker-strum-1c&quot; title=&quot;Soundmaker Strum 1c&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;Soundmaker Strum 1c&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/944144806&amp;amp;color=%236c6c6a&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral&quot; title=&quot;Mock Funeral Audio&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;Mock Funeral Audio&lt;/a&gt; · &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral/soundmaker-soundmagicfx-strum&quot; title=&quot;SoundMaker &amp;amp; SoundMagicFX: Strum 2c&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;SoundMaker &amp;amp; SoundMagicFX: Strum 2c&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/944144809&amp;amp;color=%236c6c6a&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral&quot; title=&quot;Mock Funeral Audio&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;Mock Funeral Audio&lt;/a&gt; · &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral/soundmaker-soundmagicfx-1&quot; title=&quot;SoundMaker &amp;amp; SoundMagicFX: Strum 2b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;SoundMaker &amp;amp; SoundMagicFX: Strum 2b&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/944144812&amp;amp;color=%236c6c6a&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral&quot; title=&quot;Mock Funeral Audio&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;Mock Funeral Audio&lt;/a&gt; · &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral/soundmaker-soundmagicfx-2&quot; title=&quot;SoundMaker &amp;amp; SoundMagicFX: Strum 2a&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;SoundMaker &amp;amp; SoundMagicFX: Strum 2a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting one. I tried to process a file that was a bit long and very quickly during the process rendering, it ran out of memory and cancelled the operation. Sometimes when SoundMaker does this, it will still have rendered some of the file. Sometimes when it does this, it just glitches out completely for some of the file. Absolutely lovely sounds. After this I ran the same process again and it glitched out again, but when I went to save the file, the glitching had disappeared from the file. It didn’t even appear in the waveform anymore. It was only there for a brief moment. I still haven’t been able to recreate this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/944144839&amp;amp;color=%236c6c6a&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral&quot; title=&quot;Mock Funeral Audio&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;Mock Funeral Audio&lt;/a&gt; · &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral/soundmaker-soundmagicfx-memory&quot; title=&quot;SoundMaker &amp;amp; SoundMagicFX: Memory glitch&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;SoundMaker &amp;amp; SoundMagicFX: Memory glitch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here some of the manipulated files from SoundMaker are mangled by a a ppooll patch on a modern laptop. I ought to have used lloopp for Max/MSP 4, but well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/944174428&amp;amp;color=%236c6c6a&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral&quot; title=&quot;Mock Funeral Audio&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;Mock Funeral Audio&lt;/a&gt; · &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/mockfuneral/soundmaker-soundmagicfx-ppooll-1&quot; title=&quot;SoundMaker, SoundMagicFX &amp;amp; Ppooll 1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;SoundMaker, SoundMagicFX &amp;amp; Ppooll 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;screenshots&quot;&gt;Screenshots&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Full view:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/soundmakerfull1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Soundmaker, full view&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SoundMaker effects menu:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/soundmakermenu1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;SoundMaker effects menu&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SoundMaker, Mike Norris effects menu:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/soundmakermenu2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Norris FX menu&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time varying stretch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/soundmaker_timevari.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Timevarying stretch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chunkmunger:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/soundmakerchunkmunger1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chunkmunger&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the best: the tonedialer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/soundmakertonedailer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tonedialer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Introduction</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/08/introduction"/>
   <updated>2020-12-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/08/introduction</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Written by mh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2019 I found a link online to Bhob Rainey’s Xynthi Supercollider 2 patch, which I found out didn’t run on current day OSX/macOS. I listened to the three noisy samples in the recordings folder and decided I had to try this out somehow. So the following month I got a hold of of a Powerbook from 2002, installed OSX 10.3.9 on it alongside OS9.2.2 – just for the hell of it. Might as well go further back now that I have a machine that will allow that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got Xynthi working and loved it. Absolutely loved it. I used it quite regularly throughout 2020 and made a handful of releases using the patch. During all of this I had tried to get a few pieces of OS9 software to work, but with constant crashes and errors, so I put it away for a few months and focused on Xynthi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summer of 2020 I had to go to the Netherlands for a 6-month exchange. Leaving all of my bulky gear in a basement in Copenhagen and only taking essentials, which, for some reason, also happened to include the Powerbook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November of 2020, a year after getting the Powerbook in the first place, I suddenly felt like it was time to revisit OS9 and old software in general. I made a thread on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://llllllll.co/&quot;&gt;lines forums&lt;/a&gt; to see if anyone had anything interesting to share. Software, stories, techniques, etc. Quite a lot of insightful replies later I decided to start this blog/site to archive the things people wrote. Mostly to have it be a bit more permanent than on a niche forum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here we are. A little blog to archive all these findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why even care about, let alone USE, all this old software running on terribly obsolete hardware? I can’t give a really insightful, poetic answer. I just find it fascinating. And it sounds fantastic. Different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll do my best to keep this site alive. If you have any pieces of software you would like to write a bit about, experience using it, tips, techniques, stories, let me know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact me at&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;mockfuneralmh [at] gmail [dot] com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or over at Twitter, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mockfuneral&quot;&gt;@mockfuneral&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the best and take care.
mh&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
